Poul Anderson

Ghetto

The monorail set them off at Kith Town, on the edge of the great city. Its blaze of light, red and gold and green looped between high slim towers, pulsed in the sky above them, but here it was dark and still, night had come. Kenri Shaun stood for a moment with the others, shifting awkwardly on his feet and wondering what to say. They knew he was going to resign, but the Kithman’s rule of privacy kept the words from their lips.

“Well,” he said at last, “I’ll be seeing you around.”

“Oh, sure,” said Graf Kishna. “We won’t be leaving Earth again for months yet.”

After a pause, he added: “We’ll miss you when we do go. I—wish you’d change your mind, Kenri.”

“No,” said Kenri. “I’m staying. But thanks.”

“Come see us,” invited Graf. “We’ll have to get a bunch together for a poker game sometime soon.”

“Sure. Sure I will.”

Graf s hand brushed Kenri’s shoulder, one of the Kith gestures which said more than speech ever could. “Goodnight,” he spoke aloud.

“Goodnight.”

Words murmured in the dimness. They stood there for an instant longer, half a dozen men in the loose blue doublets, baggy trousers, and soft shoes of the Kith in Town. There was a curious similarity about them, they were all of small and slender build, dark complexioned, but it was the style of movement and the expression of face which stamped them most. They had looked on strangeness all their lives, out between the stars.

Then the group dissolved and each went his own way. Kenri started toward his father’s place. There was a thin chill in the air, the northern pole was spinning into autumn, and Kenri hunched his shoulders and jammed his hands into his pockets.

The streets of the Town were narrow concrete strips, nonluminous, lit by old-style radiant globes. These threw a vague whiteness on lawns and trees and the little half-underground houses set far back from the roads. There weren’t many people abroad: an elderly officer, grave in mantle and hood; a young couple walking slowly, hand in hand; a group of children tumbling on the grass; small lithe forms filling the air with their laughter, filling themselves with the beauty and mystery which were Earth. They might have been born a hundred years ago, some of those children, and looked on worlds whose very suns were invisible here, but always the planet drew men home again. They might cross the Galaxy someday, but always they would return to murmurous forests and galloping seas, rain and wind and swift-footed clouds, though all space and time they would come back to their mother.

Most of the hemispheres Kenri passed were dark, tended only by machines while their families flitted somewhere beyond the sky. He passed the home of a friend, Jong Errifrans, and wondered when he would see him again. The Golden Flyer wasn’t due in from Betelgeuse for another Earth-century, and by then the Fleetwing, Kenri’s own ship, might well be gone—No, wait, I’m staying here. I’ll be a very old man when Jong comes back, still young and merry, still with a guitar across his shoulders and laughter on his lips. I’ll be an Earthling then.

The town held only a few thousand houses, and most of its inhabitants were away at any given time. Only the Fleetwing, the Flying Cloud, the High Barbaree, the Our Lady, and the Princess Karen were at Sol now: their crews would add up to about 1200, counting the children. He whispered the lovely, archaic names, savoring them on his tongue. Kith Town, like Kith society, was changeless; it had to be. When you traveled near the speed of light and time shrank so that you could be gone a decade and come back to find a century Clown on Earth—And here was home, where you were among your own kind and not a tommy who had to bow and wheedle the great merchants of Sol, here you could walk like a man. It wasn’t true what they said on Earth, that tommies were rootless, without planet or history or loyalty.

There was a deeper belongingness here than the feverish rise and warring and fall of Sol could ever know.

“—Good evening, Kcnri Shaun.”

He stopped, jerked out of his reverie, and looked at the young woman. The pale light of a street globe spilled across her long dark hair and down her slim shape. “Oh—” He caught himself and bowed. “Good evening to you, Theye Barinn. I haven’t seen you in a long time. Two years, isn’t it?”

“Not quite so long for me,” she said. “The High Barbaree went clear to Vega last trip. We’ve been in orbit here about an Earth-month. The Fleetwing got in a couple of weeks ago, didn’t she?”

Covering up, not daring to speak plainly. He knew she knew almost to the hour when the great spaceship had arrived from Sirius and taken her orbit about the home planet.

“Yes,” he said, “but our astrogation computer was burned out and I had to stay aboard with some others and get it fixed.”

“I know,” she answered. “I asked your parents why you weren’t in Town. Weren’t you—impatient?”

“Yes,” he said, and a thinness edged his tone. He didn’t speak of the fever that had burned in him, to get away, get downside, and go to Dorthy where she waited for him among the roses of Earth. “Yes, of course, but the ship came first, and I was the best man for the job. My father sold my share of the cargo for me; I never liked business anyway.”

Small talk, he thought, biting back the words, chatter eating away the time he could be with Dorthy. But he couldn’t quite break away, Theye was a friend. Once he had thought she might be more, but that was before he knew Dorthy.

“Things haven’t changed much since we left,” she said. “Not in twenty-five Earth-years. The Star Empire is still here, with its language and its genetic hierarchy—a little bigger, a little more hectic, a little doser to revolt or invasion and the end. I remember the Africans were much like this, a generation or two before they fell.”

“So they were,” said Kenri. “So were others. So will still others be. But I’ve heard the Stars are clamping down on us.”

“Yes.” Her voice was a whisper. “We have to buy badges now, at an outrageous price, and wear them everywhere outside the Town. It may get worse. I think it will.”

He saw that her mouth trembled a little under the strong curve of her nose, and the eyes turned up to his were suddenly filmed with a brightness of tears. “Kenri—is. it true what they’re saying about you?”

“Is what true?” Despite himself; he snapped it out.

“That you’re going to resign? Quit the Kith—become an . . . Earthling?”

“I’ll talk about it later.” It was a harshness in his throat. “I haven’t time now.”

“But Kenri—” She drew a long breath and pulled her hand back.

“Goodnight, Theye. I’ll see you later. I have to hurry.”

He bowed and went on, quickly, not looking back. The lights and the shadows slid their bars across him as he walked.

Dorthy was waiting, and he would see her tonight. But just then he couldn’t feel happy about it, somehow.

He felt like hell.

She had stood at the vision port, looking out into a dark that crawled with otherness, and the white light of the ship’s walk. had been cool in her hair. He came softly behind her and thought again what a wonder she was. Even a millennium ago, such tall slender blondes had been rare on Earth. If the human breeders of the Star Empire had done nothing else, they should be remembered with love for having created her kind.

She turned around quickly, sensing him with a keeness of perception he could not match. The silver-blue eyes were enormous on him, and her lips parted a little, half covered by one slim band. He thought what a beautiful thing a woman’s hand was. “You startled me, Kenri Shaun.”

“I am sorry, Freelady,” he said contritely.

“It—” She smiled with a hint of shakiness. “It is nothing. I am too nervous—don’t know interstellar space at all.”

“It can be . . . unsettling, I suppose, if you aren’t used to it, Freelady,” he said. “I was born between the stars, myself”

She shivered faintly under the thin blue tunic. “It it too big,” she said. “Too big and old and strange for us, Kenri Shaun. I thought traveling between the planets was something beyond human understanding, but this—” Her band touched his, and his fingers closed on it, almost against his own will. “This is like nothing I ever imagined.”

“When you travel nearly at the speed of light,” he said, covering his shyness with pedantry, “you can’t expect conditions to be the same. Aberration displaces the stars, and Doppler effect changes the color. That’s all, Freelady.”

The ship hummed around them, as if talking to herself Dorthy had once wondered what the vessel’s robot brain thought—what it felt like to be a spaceship, forever a wanderer between foreign skies. He had told her the robot lacked consciousness, but the idea had haunted him since. Maybe only because it was Dorthy’s idea.

“It’s the time shrinking that frightens me most, perhaps,” she said. Her hand remained in his, the fingers tightening. He sensed the faint wild perfume she wore, it was a heady draught in his nostrils. “You—I can’t get over the fact that you were born a thousand years ago, Kenri Shaun. That you will still be traveling between the stars when I am down in dust.”

It was an obvious opening for a compliment, but his tongue was locked with awkwardness. He was a space farer, a Kithrnan, a dirty slimy tommy, and she was Star-Free, unspecialized genius, the finest flower of the Empire’s genetic hierarchy. He said only: “It is no paradox, Freelady. As the relative velocity approaches that of light, the measured time interval decreases, just as the mass increases; but only to a ‘stationary’ observer. One set of measurements is as ‘real’ as another. We’re running with a tau factor of about 33 this trip, which means that it takes us some four months to go from Sirius to Sol; but to a watcher at either star, we’ll take almost eleven years.” His mouth felt shff, but he twisted it into a smile. “That’s not so long, Freelady. You’ll have been gone, let’s see, twice eleven plus a year in the Sirian System—twenty-four years. Your estates will still be there.”

“Doesn’t it take an awful reaction mass?” she asked. A fine line appeared on the broad forehead as she frowned, trying to understand

“No, Freelady. Or, rather, it does, but we don’t have to expel matter as an interplanetary ship must. The field drive reacts directly against the mass of local stars—theoretically the entire universe—and converts our mercury ‘ballast’ into kinetic energy for the rest of the ship. It acts equally on all mass, so we don’t experience acceleration pressure and can approach light speed in a few days. In fact, if we didn’t rotate the ship, we’d be weightless. When we reach Sol, the agoratron will convert the energy back into mercury atoms and we’ll again be almost stationary with respect to Earth.”

“I’m afraid I never was much good at physics,” she laughed “W”e leave that to Star-A and Norm-A types on Earth.”

The sense of rejection was strangling in him. Yes, he thought, brain work and muscle work are still just work. Let the inferiors sweat over it, Star-Frees need all their time just to be ornamental. Her fingers had relaxed, and he drew his hand back to him.

She looked pained, sensing his hurt, and reached impulsively out to touch his cheek. “I’m sorry,” she said quietly. “I didn’t mean to .. I didn’t mean what you think.”

“It is nothing, Freelady,” he said stiffly, to cover his bewilderment. That an aristocrat should apologize—!

“But it is much,” she said earnestly. “I know how many people there are who don’t like the Kith. You just don’t fit into our society, you realize that. You’ve never really belonged on Earth.” A slow flush crept up her pale cheeks, and she looked down. Her lashes were long and smoky black. “But 1 do know a little about people, Kenri Shaun. I know a superior type when I meet it. You could be a Star-Free yourself except . . . we might bore you.”

“Never that, Freelady,” he said thickly.

He had gone away from her with a singing in him. Three months, he thought gloriously, three ship-months yet before they came to Sol.

A hedge rustled dryly as he turned in at the Shaun gate. Overhead, a maple tree stirred, talking to the light wind, and fluttered a blood-colored leaf down on him. Early frost this year, he thought. The weather-control system had never been rebuilt after the Mechanoclasts abolished it, and maybe they had been right there, He paused to inhale the smell of the wind. It was cool and damp, full of odors from mould and turned earth and ripened berries. It struck him suddenly that he had never been here during a winter. He had never seen the hills turn white and glittering, or known the immense hush of snowfall.

Warm yellow light spilled out to make circles on the lawn. He put his hand on the doorplate, it scanned his pattern and the door opened for him. When he walked into the small, cluttered living room, crowded with half a dozen kids, he caught the lingering whiff of dinner and regretted being too late for it. He’d eaten on shipboard, but there was no cook in the Galaxy quite like his mother.

He saluted his parents as custom prescribed, and his father nodded gravely. His mother was less restrained, she hugged him and said how thin he had gotten. The kids said hello and went back to their books and games and chatter. They’d seen their older brother often enough, and were too young to realize what his decision of resigning meant.

“Come, Kenri, I will fix a sandwich for you at least—” said his mother. “It is. good to have you back.”

“I haven’t time,” he said. Helplessly: “I’d like to, but—well—I have to go out again.”

She turned away. “Theye Sarin was asking about you,” she said, elaborately casual. “The High Barbaree got back an Earth-month ago.”

“Oh, yes,” he said. “I met her on the street.”

“Theye is a nice girl,” said his mother. “You ought to go call on her. It’s not too late tonight.”

“Some other time,” he said.

“The High Barbaree is off to Tau Ceti in another two months,” said his mother. “You won’t have much chance to see Theye, unless—” Her voice trailed off. Unless you marry her, She’s your sort, Kenri. She would belong well on the Fleetwing. She would give me strong grandchildren,

“Some other time,” he repeated. He regretted the brusqueness in his tone, but he couldn’t help it. Turning to his father: “Dad, what’s this about a new tax on us?”

Volden Shaun scowled. “A damned imposition,” he said. “May all their spacesuits spring leaks. We have to wear these badges now, and pay through the nose for them.”

“Can . . . can I borrow yours for tonight? I have to go into the city.”

Slowly, Volden met the eyes of his son. Then he sighed and got up. “It’s in my study,” he said. “Come along and help me find it.”

They entered the little room together. It was filled with Volden’s books—he read on every imaginable subjects, like most Kithmen—and his carefully polished astrogation instruments and his mementos of other voyages. It all meant something. That intricately chased sword had been given him by an armorer on Procyon V, a many-armed monster who had been his friend. That stereograph was a view of the sharp hills on Isis, frozen gases like molten amber in the glow of mighty Osiris. That set of antlers was from a hunting trip on Loki, in the days of his youth. That light, leaping statuette had been a god on Dagon. Volden’s dose-cropped gray head bent over the desk, his hands fumbling among the papers.

“Do you really mean to go through with this resignation?” he asked quietly.

Kenri’s face grew warm. “Yes,” he said. “I’m sorry, but—Yes.”

“I’ve seen others do it,” said Volden. “They even prospered, most of them. But I don’t think they were ever very happy.”

“I wonder,” said Kenri.

“The Fleetwing’s next trip will probably be clear to Rigel,” said Volden. “We won’t be back for more than a thousand years. There won’t be any Star Empire here. Your very name will be forgotten.”

“I heard talk about that voyage.” Kenri’s voice thickened a little. “It’s one reason I’m staying behind.”

Volden looked up, challengingly. “What’s so good about the Stars?” he asked. “I’ve seen twelve hundred years of human history, good times and bad times. This is not one of the good times. And it’s going to get worse.”

Kenri didn’t answer.

“That girl is out of your class, son,” said Volden.

“She’s a Star-Free. You’re just a damn filthy tommy.”

“The prejudice against us isn’t racial,” said Kenri, avoiding his father’s gaze. “It’s cultural. A spaceman who goes terrestrial is . . . all right by them.”

“So far,” said Volden. “It’s beginning to get racial already, though. We may all have to abandon Earth for a while.”

“I’ll get into her class,” said Kenri. “Give me that badge.”

Volden sighed. “We’ll have to overhaul the ship to raise our tau factor,” he said. “You’ve got a good six months yet. We won’t leave any sooner. I hope you’ll change your mind.”

“I might,” said Kenri, and knew he lied in his teeth.

“Here it is.” Volden held out a small yellow loop of braided cords. “Pin it on your jacket.” He took forth a heavy wallet. “And here is a thousand decards of your money. You’ve got fifty thousand more in the bank, but don’t let this get stolen.”

Kenri fastened the symbol on. It seemed to have weight, like a stone around his neck. He was saved from deeper humiliation by the automatic reaction of his mind. Fifty thousand decards ... what to buy? A spaceman necessarily invested in tangible and lasting property.

Then he remembered that he would be staying here. The money ought to have value during his lifetime, at least. And money had a way of greasing the skids of prejudice.

“I’ll be back . . . tomorrow, maybe,” he said. “Thanks, Dad. Goodnight.”

Volden’s gaunt face drew into tighter lines. His voice was toneless, but it caught just a little. “Goodnight, son,” he said.

Kenri went out the door, into the darkness of Earth.

The first time, neither of them had been much impressed. Captain Seralpin had told Kennri: “We’ve got us another passenger. She’s over at Landfall, on Ishtar. Want to pick her up?”

“Let her stay there till we’re ready to leave,” said Kenri. “Why would she want to spend a month on Marduk?”

Seralpin shrugged: “I don’t know or care. But she’ll pay for conveyance here. Take Boat Five,” he said.

Kenri had fueled up the little interplanetary flitter and shot away from the Fleetwing, grumbling to himself Ishtar was on the other side of Sirius at the moment, and even on an acceleration orbit it took days to get there. He spent the time studying Murinn’s General Cosmology, a book he’d never gotten around to before though it was a good 2500 years old. There had been no basic advance in science since the fall of the African Empire, he reflected, and on Earth today the conviction was that all the important questions had been answered. After all, the universe was finite, so the scientific horizon must be too; after several hundred years during which research turned up no phenomenon not already predicted by theory, there would naturally be a loss of interest which ultimately became a dogma.

Kenri wasn’t sure the dogma was right. He had seen too much of the cosmos to have any great faith in man’s ability to understand it. There were problems in a hundred fields—physics, chemistry, biology, psychology, history, epistemology—to which the Nine Books gave no quantitative answer; but when he tried to tell an Earthling that, he got a blank look or a superior smile . . . . No, science was a social enterprise, it couldn’t exist when the society didn’t want it. But no civilization lasts forever. Someday there would again be a questioning.

Most of the Fleetwing’s passengers were time-expired engineers or planters returning home. Few of the big ships had ever transported a Star aristocrat. When he came down to Landfall, in a spurning rain, and walked through the hot wet streets and onto the bowered verandah of the town’s hostel, it was a shock to find that his cargo was a young and beautiful woman. He bowed to her, crossing arms on breast as prescribed, and felt the stiffness of embarrassment. He was the outsider, the inferior, the space tramp, and she was one of Earth’s owners.

“I hope the boat will not be too uncomfortable for you, Freelady,” he mumbled, and hated himself for the obsequiousness of it. He should have said, you useless brainless bitch, my people keep Earth alive and you ought to be kneeling to me in thank. But he bowed again instead, and helped her up the ladder into the cramped cabin.

“I’ll make out,” she laughed. She was too young, he guessed, to have taken on the snotty manners of her class. The fog of Ishtar lay in cool drops in her hair, like small jewels. The blue eyes were not unfriendly as they rested on his sharp dark face.

He computed an orbit back to Marduk. “It’ll take us four-plus days, Freelady,” he said. “I hope you aren’t in too much of a hurry.”

“Oh, no,” she said. “I just wanted to see that planet too, before, leaving.” He thought of what it must be costing her, ana’felt a vague sense of outrage that anyone should throw good money around on mere tourism; but he only nodded.

They were in space before long. He emerged from his curtained bunk after a few hours’ sleep to find her already up, leafing through Murinn. “I don’t understand a word of it,” she said. “Does he ever use one syllable where six will do?”

“He cared a great deal for precision, Freelady,” said Kenri as he started breakfast. Impulsively, he added: “I would have liked to know him.”

Her eyes wandered around the boat’s library, shelf on shelf of microbooks and full-sized volumes. “You people do a lot of reading, don’t you?” she asked.

“Not too much else to do on a long voyage, Freelady,” he said. “There are handicrafts, of course, and the preparation of goods for sale—things like that—but there’s still plenty of time for reading.”

“I’m surprised you have such big crews,” she said. “Surely you don’t need that many people to man a ship.’’

“No, Freelady,” he replied. “A ship between the stars just about runs herself But when we reach a planet, a lot of handr are needed”

“There’s company too, I suppose,” she ventured. “Wives and children and friends.”

“Yes, Freelady.” His voice grew cold._ What business of hers was it?

“I like your Town,” she said. “I used to go there often. It’s so—quaint? Like a bit of the past, kept alive all these centuries.”

Sure, he wanted to say, sure, your sort come around to stare. You come around drunk, and peer into our homes, and when an old man goes by you remark what a funny little geezer be is, without even lowering your voices, and when you bargain with a shopkeeper and he tries to get a fair price it only proves to you that all Commies think of nothing but money. Oh, yes, we’re very glad to have you visit us. “Yes, Freela4.”

She looked hurt, and said little for many hours. After a while she went back into the space he has screened off for her, and he heard her playing a violin. It was a very old melody, older than man’s starward wish, unbelievably old, and still it was young and tender and trustful, still it was everything which was good and dear in man. He couldn’t quite track down the music, what was it—? After a while, she stopped. He felt a desire to impress her. The Kith had their own tunes. He got out his guitar and strummed a few chords and let his mind wander.

Presently he began to sing.

“When Jerry Clawson was a baby
On his mother’s knee in old Kentuck,
He said: ‘I’m gonna ride those deep-space rockets
Till the bones in my body turn to dust.’—”

He sensed her come quietly out and stand behind him, but pretended not to be aware of her. His voice lilted between the thrumming walls, and he looked out toward cold stars and the ruddy crescent of Marduk.

“Jerry’s voice came o’er the speaker:
‘Cut your cable and go free.
On full thrust, she’s blown more shielding.
Radiation’s got to me.
‘Take the boats in safety Earthward.
Tell the Fireball Line for me
I was born to ride through deep space,
Now in deep space forevermore I’ll be.’”

He ended it with a crash of strings and looked around and got up to bow.

“No . . . sit down,” she said. “This irn’ t Earth.

What was that song?”

“Jerry Clawson, Freelady,” he replied. “It’s ancient—in fact, I was singing a translation from the original English. It goes clear back to the early days of interplanetary travel.”

Star-Frees were supposed to be intellectuals as well as esthetes. He waited for her to say that somebody ought to collect Kith folk ballads in a book.

“I like it,” she said “I like it very much.”

He looked away. “Thank you, Freelady,” he said. “May I make bold to ask what you were playing earlier?”

“Oh . . . that’s even older,” she said. “A theme from the Kreutzer Sonata. I’m awfully fond of it.” She smiled slowly. “I think I would have liked to know Beethoven.”

They met each other’s eyes, then, and did not look away or speak for what seemed like a long time.

The Town ended as sharply as if cut off by a knife. It had been like that for 3000 years, a sanctuary from time: sometimes it stood alone on open windy moors, with no other work of man in sight except a few broken walls; sometimes it was altogether swallowed by a roaring, monster of a city; sometimes, as now, it lay on the fringe of a great commune; but always it was the Town, changeless and inviolate.

No—not so. There had been days when war swept through it, pockmarking walls and sundering roofs and filling its streets with corpses; there had been murderous mobs looking for a tommy to lynch; there had been haughty swaggering officers come to enforce some new proclamation. They could return. Through all the endless turmoil of history, they would. Kenri shivered in the wandering autumn breeze and started off along the nearest avenue.

The neighborhood was a slum at the moment, gaunt crumbling tenements, cheerless lanes, aimlessly drifting crowds. They wore doublets and kilts of sleazy gray, and they stank. Most of them were Norms, nominally free—which meant free to starve when there wasn’t work to be had. The majority were Norm-Ds, low-dass manual laborers with dull heavy faces, but here and there the more alert countenance of a Norm-C or B showed briefly in the glare of a lamp, above the weaving, sliding shadows. When a Standard pushed through, gay in the livery of the state or his private owner, something flickered in those eyes. A growing knowledge, a feeling that something was wrong when slaves were better off than freemen—Kenri had seen that look before, and knew what it could become: the blind face of destruction. And elsewhere were the men of Mars and Venus and the Jovian moons, yes, the Radiant of Jupiter had ambitions and Earth was still the richest planet .. . No, he thought, the Star Empire wouldn’t last much longer.

But it ought to last his and Dorthy’s lifetime, and they could make some provision for their children. That was enough.

An elbow jarred into his ribs. “Outta the way, tommy!”

He clenched his fists, thinking of what he had done beyond the sky, what he could do here on Earth—Silently, he stepped off the walk. A woman, leaning fat and blowsy from an upstairs window, jeered at him and spat. He dodged the fleck of spittle, but he could not dodge the laughter that followed him.

They hate, he thought. They still don’t are resent their masters, so they take it out on us. Be patient. It cannot endure another two centuries.

It still shook in him, though. He grew aware of the tautness in his nerves and belly, and his neck ached with the strain of keeping his face humbly lowered. Though Dorthy was waiting for him in a garden of roses, he needed a drink. He saw the winking neon bottle and turned in that door.

A few sullen men were slumped at tables, under the jerky obscenity of a live mural that must be a hundred years old. The tavern owned only half a dozen Standard-D girls, and they were raddled things who must have been bought third hand. One of them gave Kenri a mechanical smile, saw his face and dress and badge, and turned away with a sniff.

He made his way to the bar. There was a live tender who showed him a glazed stare. “Vodzan,” said Kenri. “Make it a double.”

“We don’t serve no tommies here, said the bartender.

Kenri’s fingers whitened on the bar. He turned to go, but a hand touched his arm. “Just a minute, spaceman.” To the attendant: “One double vodzan.”

“I told you—”

“This is for me, Wilm. And I can give it to anyone I want. I can pour it on the floor if I so desire.” There was a thinness in the tone, and the bartender went quickly off to his bottles.

Kenri looked into a white, hairless face with a rakish cast to its skull structure. The lean gray-clad body was hunched over the bar, one hand idly rolling dice from a cup. There were no bones in the fingers, they were small delicate tentacles; and the eyes were colored like ruby.

“Thank you,” said Kenri. “May I pay—”

“No. It’s on me.” The other accepted the glass and handed it over. “Here.”

“Your health, sir.” Kenri lifted the glass and drank. The liquor was pungent fire along his throat.

“Such as it is,” said the man indifferently. “No trouble to me. What I say here goes.” He was probably a petty criminal of some sort, perhaps a member of the now outlawed Assassins’ Guild. And the body type was not quite human. He must be a Special-X, created in the genetic labs for a particular job or for study or for amusement. Presumably he had been set free when his owner was done with him, and had made a place for himself in the slums.

“Been gone long?” he asked, looking at the dice. “About twenty-three years,” said Kenri. “Sirius.”

“Things have changed,” said the X. “AntiKithism is growing strong again: Be careful you aren’t slugged or robbed, because if you are, it’ll do you no good to appeal to the city guards.”

“It’s nice of you to—”

“Nothing.” The slim fingers scooped up the dice and rattled the cup again. “I like somebody to feel superior to.”

“Oh.” Kenri set the glass down. For a moment, the smoky room blurred. “I see. Well—”

“No, don’t go off.” The ruby eyes lifted up to his, and he was surprised to see tears in them. “I’m sorry. You can’t blame me for being bitter. I wanted to sign on myself, once, and they wouldn’t have me.”

Kenri said nothing.

“I would, of course, give my left leg to the breastbone for a chance to go on just one voyage,” said the X dully. “Don’t you think an Earthling has his dreams now and then—we too? But I wouldn’t be much use. You have to grow up in space, damn near, to know enough to be of value on some planet Earth never heard of. And I suppose there’s my looks too. Even the underdogs can’t get together any more.”

“They never could, sir,” said Kenri.

“I suppose you’re right. You’ve seen more of both space and time than I ever will. So I stay here, belonging nowhere, and keep alive somehow; but I wonder if it’s worth the trouble. A man isn’t really alive till he has something bigger than himself and his own little happiness, for which he’d gladly die. Oh, well.” The X rolled—out the dice. “Nine. I’m losing my touch.” Glancing up again: “I know a place where they don’t care who you are if you’ve got money.”

“Thank you, sir; but I have business elsewhere,” said Kenri awkwardly.

“I thought so. Well, go ahead, then. Don’t let me stop you.” The X looked away.

“Thank you for the drink, sir.”

“It was nothing. Come in whenever you want, I’m usually here. But don’t yarn to me about the planets out there. I don’t want to hear that.”

“Goodnight,” said Kenri.

As he walked out, the dice clattered across the bar again.

Dorthy had wanted to do some surface traveling on Marduk, get to see the planet. She could have had her pick of the colony for escorts, but she chose to ask Kenri. One did not say no to a Star, so he dropped some promising negotiations for pelts with a native chief hired a groundcar, and picked her up at the time she set.

They rode quietly for a while, until the settlement was lost behind the horizon. Here was stony desert, flamboyantly colored, naked crags and iron hills and low dusty thorn-trees sharp in the thin clear air. Overhead, the sky was a royal blue, with the shrunken dirc of Sirius A and the brilliant spark of its companion spilling harsh light over the stillness.

“This is a beautiful world,” she said at last. Her tones came muffled through the tenuous air. “I like it better than Ishtar.”

“Most people don’t, Freelady,” he answered. “They call it dull and cold and dry.”

“They don’t know,” she said. Her fair head was turned from him, looking at the fantastic loom of a nearby scarp, gnawed rocks and straggling brush, tawny color streaked with the blue and red lightning of mineral veins.

“I envy you, Kenri Shaun,” she said at last. “I’ve seen a few pictures, read a few books—everything I could get hold of but it isn’t enough. When I think of all you have seen that is strange and beautiful and wonderful, I envy you.”

He ventured a question: “Was that why you came to Sirius, Freelady?”

“In par!, When my father died, we wanted someone to check on the family’s Ishtarian holdings. Evelyone assumed we’d just send an agent, but I insisted on going myself and booked with the Temeraise. They all thought I was cunny. Why, I’d come back to new styles, new slang, new people ... my friends would all be middle-aged, I’d be a walking anachronism . . . you know.” She sighed “But it was worth it.”

He thought of his own life, the grinding sameness of the voyages, week slipping into months and years within a pulsing metal shell; approach, strangeness, the savage hostility of cruel planets—he had seen friends buried under landslides, spitting out their lungs when helmets cracked open in airlessness, rotting alive with some alien sickness; he had told them goodbye and watched them go off into a silence which never gave them back and had wondered how they came to die; and on Earth he was a ghost, not belonging, adrift above the great river of time, on Earth he felt somehow unreal. “I wonder, Freelady,” he said.

“Oh, I’ll adjust,” she laughed.

The car ground its way over high dunes and down tumbling ravines, it left a track in the dust which the slow wind erased behind them. That night they camped near the ruins of a forgotten city, a place which must once have been a faerie spectacle of loveliness. Kenri set up the two tents and started a meal on the glower while she watched. “Let me help,” she offered once.

“It isn’t fitting, Freelady,” he replied. And you’d be too clumsy anyway, you’d only make a mess of it. His hands were deft on the primitive skillet. The ruddy light of the glower beat against darkness, etching their faces red in windy shadows. Overhead, the stars were high and cold.

She looked at the sputtering meal. “I thought you . . . people never ate fish,” she murmured.

“Some of us do, some don’t, Freelady,” he said absently. Out here, it was hard to resent the gulf between them. “It was originally tabooed by custom in the Kith back when space and energy for growing food on shipboard were at a premium. Only a rich man could have afforded an aquarium, you see; and a tight-knit group of nomads has to ban conspicuous consumption to prevent ill feeling. Nowadays, when the economic reason has long disappeared, only the older people still observe the taboo.”

She smiled, accepting the plate he handed her. “It’s funny,” she said. “One just doesn’t think of your people as having a history. You’ve always been around.”

Oh, we do, Freelady. We’ve plenty of traditions

—than the rest of mankind, perhaps.”

A hunting marcat screamed in the night. She shivered. “What’s that?”

“Local carnivore, Freelady. Don’t let it worry you.” He slapped his slug-thrower, obscurely pleased at a chance to show—what? Manliness? “No one with a weapon has to fear any larger animals. It’s other things that make the danger—occasionally a disease,, more often cold or heat or poison gases or vacuum or whatever hell the universe can brew for us.” He grinned, a flash of teeth in the dark lean face. “Anyway, if it ate us it would die pretty quickly. We’re as poisonous to it as it is to us.”

“Different biochemistry and ecology,” she nodded. “A billion’ or more years of separate evolution. It would be strange, wouldn’t it, if more than a very few planets had developed life so close to Earth’s that we could eat it. I suppose that’s why there never was any real extrasolar colonization—just a few settlements for mining or trading or extracting organic chemicals.”

“That’s partly it, Freelady,” he said. “Matter of economics, too. It was much easier—in money terms, cheaper—for people to stay at home; no significant percentage of them could ever have been taken away in any event—human breeding would have raised the population faster than emigration could lower it.”

She gave him a steady look. When she spoke, her voice was soft. “You Kithmen are a brainy lot, aren’t you?”

He knew it was true, but he made the expected disclaimer.

“No, no,” she said. “I’ve read up on your history a little. Correct me if wrong, but since the earliest times of space travel the qualifications have been pretty rigid. A spaceman just had to be of high intelligence, with quick reactions and stable personality both. And he couldn’t be too large, physically; but he had to be tough. And a dark complexion must be of some small help, now and then, in strong sunlight or radiation . . . Yes, that was how it was. How it still is. When women began going to space too, the trade naturally tended to run in families.

Those spacemen who didn’t fit into the life, dropped out; and the recruits from Sol were pretty similar in mind and body to the people they joined. So eventually you got the Kith—almost a separate race of man; and it evolved its own ways of living. Until at last you had a monopoly on space traffic.”

“No, Freelady,” he said “We’ve never had that. Anyone who wants to build a spaceship and man it himself can do so. But it’s an enormous capital investment; and after the initial glamour had worn off, the average Solarian just wasn’t interested in a hard and lonely life. So today, all spacemen are Kith-men, but it was never planned that way.”

“That’s what I meant,” she said. Earnestly. “And your being different naturally brought suspicion and discrimination . . . No, don’t interrupt, I want to say this through . . . . Any conspicuous minority which offers competition to the majority is going to be disliked. Sol has to have the fissionables you bring from the stars, we’ve used up our own; and the unearthly chemicals you bring are often of great value, and the trade in luxuries like furs and jewels is brisk. So you are essential to society, but you still don’t really belong in it. You are too proud, in your own way, to ape your. oppressors. Being human, you naturally charge all the traffic will bear, which gives you the reputation of being gouger; being able to think better and faster than the average Solarian, you can usually best him in a deal, and he hates you for it. Then there’s the tradition handed down from Mechanoclastic times, when technology was considered evil and only you maintained a high level of it. And in the puritan stage of the Martian conquest, your custom of wife trading—oh, I know you do it just to relieve the endless monotony of the voyages, I know you have more family life than we do—Well, all those times are gone, but they’ve left their legacy. I wonder why you bother with Earth at all. Why you don’t all just wander into space and let us stew in our own juice.”

“Earth is our planet too, Freelaa’y,” he said, very quietly. After a moment: “The fact that we are essential gives us some protection. We get by. Please don’t fed sorry for us.”

“A stiff-necked people,” she said. “You don’t even want pity.”

“Who does, Freelady?” he asked.

On the edge of the slum, in a zone bulking with the tall warehouses and offices of the merchant families, Kenri took an elevator up to the public skyway going toward the address he wanted. There was no one else in sight at that point; he found a seat and lowered himself into it and let the strip hum him toward city center.

The skyway climbed fast, until he was above all but the highest towers. Leaning an arm on the rail, he looked down into a night that was alive with radiance. The streets and walls glowed, strings of colored lamps flashed and flashed against a velvet dark, fountains leaped white and gold and scarlet, a flame display danced like molten rainbows at the feet of a triumphal statue. Star architecture was a thing of frozen , motion, soaring columns and tiers and pinnacles to challenge the biirning sky; high in that airy jungle, the spaceman could hardly make out the river of vehicles and humanity below him.

As he neared the middle of town, the skyway gathered more passengers. Standards in bright fantastic livery, Norms in their tunics and kilts, an occasional visitor from Mars or Venus or Jupiter with resplendent uniform and greedy smoldering eyes—yes, and here came a party of Frees, their thin garments, a swirling iridescence about the erect slender forms, a hard glitter of jewels, the men’s beards and the women’s hair elaborately curled. Fashions had changed in the past two decades. Kenri felt acutely aware of his own shabbiness, and huddled doser to the edge of the strip.

Two young couples passed his seat. He caught a woman’s voice: “Oh, look, a tommy!”

“He’s got a nerve,” mumbled one of the men. “I’ve half a mind to—”

“No, Scanish.” Another feminine voice, gentler than the first. “He has the right.”

“He shouldn’t have. I know these tommies. Give ‘em a finger and they’ll take your whole arm.” The four were settling into the seat behind Kenri’s. “My uncle is in Transsolar Trading. He’ll tell you.”

“Please, no, Scanish, he’s listening!”

“And I hope he—”

“Never mind, dear. What shall we do next? Go to Halgor’s?” She attempted a show of interest.

“Ah, we’ve been there a hundred times. What is there to do? How about getting my rocket and shooting over to China? I know a place where they got techniques you never—”

“No. I’m not in the mood. I don’t know what I want to do.”

“My nerves have been terrible lately. We bought a new doctor, but he says just the same as the old one. They don’t any of them know which end is up. I might try this new Beltanist religion, they seem to have something. It would at least be amusing.”

“Say, have you heard about Marla’s latest? You know who was seen coming out of her bedroom last ten-day?”

Kenri grabbed hold of his mind and forced it away from listening. He didn’t want to. He wouldn’t let the weariness and sickness of spirit which was the old tired Empire invade him.

Dorthy, he thought. Dorthy Penis from Canda. It’s a beautiful name, isn’t it? There’s music in it. And the flan Candas have always been an outstanding family. She isn’t like the rest of the Stars.

She loves me, he thought with a singing in him. She loves me. There is a life before us. Two of us, one life, and the rest of the Empire can rot as it will. We’ll be together.

He saw the skyscraper ahead of him now, a thing of stone and crystal and light that climbed toward heaven in one great rush. The insigne of the from Candas burned on its facade, an ancient and proud symbol. It stood for 300 years of achievement.

But that’s less than my own lifetime. No, I don’t have to be ashamed in their presence. I come of the oldest and best line of all humanity. I’ll fit in.

He wondered why he could not shake off the depression that douded him. This was a moment of glory. He should be going to her as a conqueror. But—

He sighed and rose as his stop approached.

Pain stabbed at him. He jumped, stumbled, and fell to one knee. Slowly, his head twisted around. The young Star grinned in his face, holding up a shockstick. Kenri’s hand rubbed the pain, and the four people began to laugh. So did everyone else in sight. The laughter followed him off the skyway and down to the ground.

There was no one else on the bridge. One man was plenty to stand watch, here in the huge emptiness between suns. The room was a hollow cavern of twilight, quiet except for the endless throbbing of the ship. Here and there, the muted light of instrument panels glowed, and the weird radiance of the distorted stars flamed in the viewport. But otherwise there was no illumination, Kenri had switched it off.

She came through the door and paused, her gown white in the dusk. His throat tightened as he looked at her, and when he bowed, his head swam. There was a faint sweet rustling as she walked closer. She had the long swinging stride of freedom, and her unbound hair floated silkily behind her.

“I’ve never been on a bridge before,” she said. “I didn’t think passengers were allowed there.”

“I invited you, Freelady, he answered, his voice catching.

“It was good of you, Kenri Shaun.” Her fingers fluttered across hir arm. “You have always been good to me.”

“Could anyone be anything else, to you?” he asked.

Light stole along her cheeks and into the eyes that turned up at his. She smiled with a strangely timid curve of lips. “Thank you,” she whispered

“Ah, I, well—” He gestured at the viewport, which seemed to hang above their heads. “That is precisely on the ship’s axis of rotation, Freelady,” he said. “That’s why the view is constant. Naturally, ‘down’ on the bridge is any point at which you are standing. You’ll note that the desks and panels are arranged in a circle around the inner wall, to take advantage of that fact.” His voice sounded remote and strange to his ears. “Now here we have the astrogation computer. Ours is badly in need of overhauling just now, which is why you see all those book and calculations on my desk—”

Her hand brushed the back of his chair. “This is yours, Kenri Shaun? I can almost see you working away on it, with that funny tight look on your face, as if the problem were your personal enemy. Then you sigh, and run your fingers through your hair, and put your feet on the desk to think for a while. Am I right?”

“How did you guess, Freelady?”

“I know. I’ve thought a great deal about you, lately.” She looked away, out to the harsh blue-white stars clustered in the viewport.

Suddenly her fists gathered themselves. “I wish you didn’t make me feel so futile,” she said.

“You—”

“This is life, here.” She spoke swiftly, blurring the words in her need to say them. “You’re keeping Earth alive, with your cargoes. You’re working and fighting and thinking about—about something real.

Not about what to wear for dinner and who was seen where with whom and what to do tonight when you’re too restless and unhappy to stay quietly at home. You’re keeping Earth alive, I said, and a dream too. I envy you, Kenri Shaun. I wish I were born into the Kith.”

“Freelady—” It rattled in his throat.

“No use.” She smiled, without self-pity. “Even if a ship would have me, I could never go. I don’t have the training, or the inborn strength, or the patience, or—No! Forget it.” There were tears in the ardent eyes. “When I get home, knowing now what you are in the Kith, will I even try to help you? Will I work for more understanding of your people, kindness, common decency? No. I’ll realize it’s useless even to try. I won’t have the courage.”

“You’d be wasting your time, Freelady,” he said. “No one person can change a whole culture. Don’t worry about it.”

“I know,” she replied. “You’re right, of course. You’re always right. But in my place, you would try”

They stared at each other for a long moment. That was the first time he kissed her.

The two guards at the soaring main entrance were giants, immobile as statues in the sunburst glory of their uniforms. Kenri had to crane his neck to look into the face of the nearest. “The Freelady Dorthy Persis is expecting me,” he said.

“Huh?” Shock brought the massive jaw clicking down.

“That’s right.” Kenri grinned and extended the card she had given him. “She said to look her up immediately.”

“But—there’s a party going on—”

“Never mind. Call her up.”

The guardsman reddened, opened his mouth, and snapped it shut again. Turning, he went to the visiphone booth. Kenri waited, regretting his insolence. Give ‘em a finger and they’ll take your whole arm. But how else could a Kithman behave? If he gave deference, they called him a servile bootlicker; if he showed his pride, he was an obnoxious pushing bastard; if he dickered for a fair price, he was a squeezer and bloodsucker; if he spoke his own old language to his comrades, he was being secretive; if he cared more for his skyfaring people than for an ephemeral nation, he was a traitor and coward; if—

The guard returned, shaking his head in astonishment. “All right,” he said sullenly. “Go on up. First elevator to your right, fiftieth floor. But watch your manners, tommy.”

When I’m adopted into the masters, thought Kenri savagely, I’ll make him eat that word. Then, with a new rising of the unaccountable weariness: No. Why should I? What would anyone gain by it?

He went under the enormous curve of the door, into a foyer that was a grotto of luminous plastic. A few Standard servants goggled at him, but made no move to interfere. He found the elevator cage and punched for 50. It rose in a stillness broken only by the sudden rapid thunder of his heart.

He emerged into an anteroom of red velvet. Beyond an arched doorway, he glimpsed colors floating, a human blaze of red and purple and gold; the air was loud with music and laughter. The footman at the entrance stepped in his path, hardly believing the sight. “You can’t go in there!”

“The hell I can’t.” Kenri shoved him aside and strode through the arch. The radiance hit him like a fist, and he stood blinking at the confusion of dancers, servants, onlookers, entertainers—there must be a thousand people in the vaulted chamber.

“Kenri! Oh, Kenri—”

She was in his arms, pressing her mouth to his, drawing his head down with shaking hands. He strained her close, and the misty cloak she wore whirled about to wrap them in aloneness.

One moment, and then she drew back breathlessly, laughing a little. It wasn’t quite the merriment he had known, there was a thin note to it, and shadows lay under the great eyes. She was very tired, he saw, and pity lifted in him. “Dearest,” he whispered.

“Kenri, not here . . . Oh, darling, I hoped you would come sooner, but—No, come with me now, I want them all to see the man I’ve got with me.” She took his hand and half dragged him forward. The dancers were stopping, pair by pair as they noticed the stranger, until at last there were a thousand faces stiffly turned to his. Silence dropped like a thunderclap, but the music kept on. It sounded tinny in the sudden quiet.

Dorthy shivered. Then she threw back her head with a defiance that was dear to him and met the eyes. Her arm rose to bring the wristphone to her lips, and the ceiling amplifiers boomed her voice over the room: “Friends, I want to announce : . . Some of you already know . . well, this is the man I’m going to marry—”

It was the voice of a frightened little girl. Cruel to make it loud as a goddess talking.

After a pause which seemed to last forever, somebody performed the ritual bow. Then somebody else did, and then they were all doing it, like jointed dolls. There were a-few scornful exceptions, who turned their backs.

“Go on!” Dorthy’s tones grew shrill. “Go on dancing. Please! You’ll all—later—” The orchestra leader must have had a degree of sensitivity, for he struck up a noisy tune and one by one the couples slipped into a figure dance.

Dorthy looked hollowly up at the spaceman. “It’s good to see you again,” she said.

“And you,” he replied.

“Come.” She led him around the wall. “Let’s sit and talk.”

They found an alcove, screened from the room by a trellis of climbing roses. It was a place of dusk, and she turned hungrily to him. He felt how she trembled.

“It hasn’t been easy for you, has it?” he asked tonelessly.

“No,” she said.

“If you—”

“Don’t say it!” There was fear in the words. She closed his mouth with hers.

“I love you,” she said after a while. “That’s all that matters, isn’t it?”

He didn’t answer.

“Isn’t it?” she cried.

He nodded. “Maybe. I take it your family and friends don’t approve of your choice.”

“Some don’t. Does it matter, darling? They’ll forget, when you’re one of us.”

“One of you—I’m not born to this,” he said bleakly. “I’ll always stick out like—Well, never mind. I can stand it if you can.”

He sat on the padded bench, holding her close, and looked out through the clustered blooms. Color and, motion and high harsh laughter—it wasn’t his world. He wondered why he had ever assumed it could become his.

They had talked it out while the ship plunged through night. She could never be of the Kith. There was no room in a crew for one who couldn’t endure worlds never meant for man. He would have to join her instead. He could fit in, he had the intelligence and adaptability to make a place for himself.

What kind of place? he wondered as she nestled against him. A planner of more elaborate parties, a purveyor of trivial gossip, a polite ear for boredom and stupidity and cruelty and perversion—No, there would be Dorthy, they would be alone in the nights of Earth and that would be enough.

Would it? A man couldn’t spend all his time making love.

There were the big trading firms, he could go far in one of them. (Four thousand barrels of Kahan jung oil rec’d. pr. acct., and the fierce rains and lightning across the planet’s phosphorescent seas. A thousand refined thorium ingots from Hathor, and moonlight sparkling the crisp snow and the ringing winter stillness. A bale of green furs from a newly discovered planet, and the ship had gone racing through stars and splendor into skies no man had ever seen.) Or perhaps the military. (Up on your feet, soldier! Hup, hup, hup, hup! . . . Sir, the latest Intelligence report on Mars . . . Sir, I know the guns aren’t up to spec, but we can’t touch the contractor, his patron is a Star-Free .... The General commands your presence at a banquet for staff officers . . . . Now tell me, Colonel Shaun, tell me what you really think will happen, you officers are all so frightfully closemouthed . . . . Ready! Aim! Fire! So perish all traitors to the Empire!) Or even the science centers. (Well, sir, according to the book, the formula is . .

Kenri’s arm tightened desperately about Dorthy’s waist.

“How do you like being home?” he asked. “Otherwise, I mean.”

“Oh—fine. Wonderful!” She smiled uncertainly at him. “I was so afraid I’d be old-fashioned, out of touch; but no, I fell in right away. There’s the most terribly amusing crowd, a lot of them children of my own old crowd. You’ll love them, Kenri. I have a lot of glamour, you know; for going clear to Sirius. Think how much you’ll have!”

“I won’t,” he grunted. “I’m just a tommy, remember?”

‘Kenri!” Anger flicked across her brow. “What a way to talk. You aren’t, and you know it, and you won’t be unless you insist on thinking like one all the time—” She caught herself and said humbly: “I’m sorry, darling. That was a terrible thing to say, wasn’t it?”

He stared ahead of him.

“I’ve been, well, infected,” she said. “You were gone so long. You’ll cure me again.”

Tenderness filled him, and he kissed her. “A-hum! Pardon!”

They jerked apart, almost guiltily, and looked up to the two who had entered the alcove. One was a middle-aged man, austerely slender and erect, his night-blue tunic flashing with decorations; the other was younger, pudgy-faced, and rather drunk. Kenri got up. He bowed with his arms straight, as one equal to another.

“Oh, you must meet, I know you’ll like each other—” Dorthy was speaking fast, her voice high. “This is Kenri Shaun. I’ve told you enough about him, haven’t I?” A nervous little laugh. “Kenri, my uncle, Colonel from Canda of the Imperial Staff, and my nephew, the Honorable Lord Doms. Fancy coming back and finding you have a nephew your own age!”

“Your honor, sir.” The colonel’s voice was as stiff as his back. Doms giggled.

“You must pardon the interruption,” went on from Canda. “But I wished to speak to . . . to Shaun as soon as possible. You will understand, sir, that it is for the good of my niece and the whole family.”

Kenri’s palms were cold and wet. “Of course,” he said. “Please sit down.”

“Thank you.” From Canda lowered his angular frame onto the bench, next to the Kithman; Doms and Dorthy sat at opposite ends, the young man slumped over and grinning. “Shall I send for some wine?”

“Not for me, thanks,” said Kenri huskily.

The cold eyes were level on his. “First,” said the colonel, “I want you to realize that I do not share this absurd race prejudice which is growing up about your people. It is demonstrable that the Kith is biologically equal to the Star families, and doubtless superior to some.” His glance flickered contemptuously over to Doms. “There is a large cultural barrier, of course, but if that can be surmounted, I, for one, would be glad to sponsor your adoption into our ranks.”

“Thank you, sir.” Kenri felt dizzy. No Kithman had ever gone so high in all history. That it should be him—! He heard Dorthy’s happy little sigh as she took his arm, and something of the frozenness within him began to thaw. “I’ll . . . do best—”

“But will you? That is what I have to find out.” From Canda leaned forward, clasping his gaunt hands between his knees. “Let us not mince words. You know as well as I that there is a time of great danger ahead for the Empire, and that if it is to survive the few men of action left must stand together and strike hard. We can ill afford the weaklings among us; we can certainly not afford to have strong men in our midst who are not wholeheartedly for our cause.”

“I’ll be . . . loyal, sir,” said Kenri. “What more can I do?”

“Much,” said the colonel. “Considerable of it may be distasteful to you. Your special knowledge could be of high value. For example, the new tax on the Kith is not merely a device to humiliate them. We need the money. The Empire’s finances are in bad shape, and even that little bit helps. There will have to be further demands, on the Kith as well as everyone else. You can assist us in guiding our policy, so that they are not goaded to the point of abandoning Earth altogether.”

“I—” Kenri swallowed. He felt suddenly ill. “You can’t expect—”

“If you won’t, then you won’t, and I cannot force you,” said from Canda. There was a strange brief sympathy in the chill tones. “I am merely warning you of what lies ahead. You could mitigate the lot of your . . . former . . . people considerably, if you help us.”

“Why not . . . treat them like human beings?” asked Kenri. “We’ll always stand by our friends.”

“Three thousand years of history cannot be canceled by decree,” said from Canda. “You know that as well as I.”

Kenri nodded. It seemed to strain his neck musdes.

“I admire your courage,” said the aristocrat. “You have started on a hard road. Can you follow it through?”

Kenri looked down.

“Of course he can,” said Dorthy softly.

Lord Doms giggled. “New tax,” he said. “Slap a new one on fast. I’ve got one tommy skipper on the ropes already. Bad voyage, debts, heh!”

Red and black and icy blue, and the shriek of lifting winds.

“Shut up, Doms,” said the colonel. “I didn’t want you along.”

Dorthy’s head leaned back against Kenri’s shoulder. “Thank you, uncle,” she said. There was a lilt in her voice. “If you’ll be our friend, it will all work out.”

“I hope so,” said from Canda.

The faint sweet odor of Dorthy’s hair was in Kenri’s nostrils. He felt the gold waves brushing his cheek, but still .didn’t look up. There was thunder and darkness in him. _

Doms laughed. “I got to tell you ‘bout this spacer,” he said. “He owes the firm money, see? I can take his daughter under contract if he doesn’t pay up. Only his crew are taking up a collection for him. I got to stop that somehow. They say those tommy girls are mighty hot. How about it, Kenri? You’re one of us now. How are they, really? Is it true that—”

Kenri stood up. He saw the room swaying, and wondered dimly if he was wobbling on his feet or not.

“Doms,” snapped from Canda, “if you don’t shut your mouth—”

Kenri grabbed a handful of Lord Doms’ tunic and hauled him to his feet. The other hand became a fist, and the face squashed under it.

He stood over the young man, weaving, his arms hanging loose at his sides. Doms moaned on the floor. Dorthy gave a small scream. From Canda leaped up, clapping his hand to a sidearm.

Kenri lifted his eyes. There was a thickness in his words. “Go ahead and arrest me,” he said. “Go on, what are you waiting for?”

‘K-k-kenri—” Dorthy touched him with shaking hands.

From Canda grinned and nudged Doms with a boot. “That was foolish of you, Kenri Shaun,” he said, “but the job was long overdue. I’ll see that nothing happens to you.”

“But this Kith girl—”

“She’ll be all right too, I daresay, if her father can raise that money.” The hard eyes raked Kenri’s face. “But remember, my friend, you cannot live in two worlds at once. You are not a Kithman any longer.”

Kenri straightened. He knew a sudden dark peace, as if all storms had laid themselves to rest. His head felt a little empty, but utterly clear.

It was a memory in him which had opened his vision and shown him what he must do, the only thing he could do. There was a half-human face and eyes without hope and a voice which had spoken: “A man isn’t redly alive till he has something bigger than himself and his own little happiness, for which he’d gladly die.”

“Thank you, sir,” he said. “But ‘I am a Kithman. I will always be.”

“Kenri—” Dorthy’s tone broke. She held his arms and stared at him with wildness.

His hand stroked her hair. “I’m sorry, dearest,” he said gently.

“Kenri, you can’t go, you can’t, you can’t—”

“I must,” he said. “It was bad enough that I should give up everything which had been my life for an existence that to me is stupid and dreary and meaningless. For you, I could have stood that. But you are asking me to be a tyrant, or at least to be a friend of tyrants. You’re asking me to countenance evil. I can’t do it. I wouldn’t if I could.” He took her shoulders and looked into the unseeing bewilderment of her eyes. “Because that would, in the end, make me hate you, who had so twisted my own self, and I want to go on loving you. I will always love you.”

She wrenched away from him. He thought that there were psychological treatments to change her feelings and make her stop caring about him. Sooner or later, she’d take one of those. He wanted to kiss her farewell, but he didn’t quite dare.

Colonel from Canda extended a hand. “You will be my enemy, I suppose,” he said. “But I respect you for it. I like you, and wish—well, good luck to you, Kenri Shaun.”

“And to you, sir . . . Goodbye, Dorthy.”

He walked through the ballroom, not noticing the eyes that were on him, and out the door to the elevator. He was still too numb to feel anything, that would come later.

Theye Barinnu a nice girl, he thought somewhere on the edge of his mind. I’ll have to go around and see her soon. We could be happy together.

It seemed like a long while before he was back in the Town. Then he walked along empty streets, alone within himself, breathing the cool damp night wind of Earth.